My name is Bill Lux.
I'm Kaska Dena.
I'm part of the Dease River First Nation.
And yeah, where we are today, I want
to share with you some of my family
heritage about this area.
We're at the park, the BC Park
Tā Ch'ilā
And Tā Ch'ilā in Kaska translates to "like
a blanket full of holes."
So behind me is the mountain range called
Ne'āh'
Ne'āh' means "laying down long."
It's a standalone range that sits by itself
outside the Cassiar Mountain Range.
And it's also known as Horse Ranch Range.
So this whole area is protected as a
conservancy, the Ne'āh'
And the Tā Ch'ilā is a provincial park
that butts up to the Ne'āh'.
So this whole area, when you look across,
it's all protected.
What I'm wearing here is the Dene K'éh Kusān.
Dene K'éh Kusān: "will always be there."
That's what it means.
And this refers to the land on the
other side of the Ne'āh'.
That whole valley all the way from Lower
Post, all the way to Fort Ware, 300
kilometres of the trench that has some major,
major watersheds, like the Ketchikan and the Red
River and the Turnagain, from Sifton Pass all
the way up to the Liard.
And that whole area is absolutely pristine wilderness.
It's got a lot of history of our
people.
The Atse Dena Tunna Trail, also known as
the Davie Trail, runs from Kwadacha all the
way to Lower Post.
And it veers off from Turnagain all the
way to McDames, where my community is, the
Dease River First Nation.
And that's where our people travel seasonally.
It's the balance that's the key.
You've got to be able to protect certain
areas based on the value and where those
areas sit and where the economics sit.
And so you've got to be able to
find that balance.
And so I was very successful in trying
to encourage others to recognize that and my
contributions to that.
Because part of that is recognizing the other
parts of our ancestral homelands where there's economic
opportunities and understanding the balance.
Here's important, this is why, but more importantly
is there's the jobs, there's the training for
mining, forestry, oil and gas still exists.
It doesn't affect it.
And trying to hopefully teach that to the
next generation to say, get on board, look
at that.
You could be a guardian, right?
And if you look at this park here,
a lot of people come here and they
see the Ne'āh'.
And we have an interpretive sign up on
the hill that we're trying to establish.
So when they they're interested about this area,
they go up there and they push button
and then one of our elders will tell
the story, right?
And they'll speak in Kaska or they'll tell
the story about the Ne'āh' and gives them
a bit more.
And then we'll have pamphlets here so they
can pick it up and talk about, oh,
what's this mountain's name?
And right.
And to be able to come back here
every year with their families.
It's a beautiful thing.
I think it's not only teaching them, but
it's helping them to recognize the opportunity of
what this brings and the fact that it'll
always be here for that opportunity, not just
for them, but for their their kids and
their grandkids to be able to bring them
up here and fish and camp, knowing that
this will always be here.
This view will never change.
My grandfather and grandmother lived on the other
side of Ne'āh' and they raised 22 kids
in that area and in that family area.
And our family area goes from from Ne'āh'
all the way to the to the Red
River, up to the Turnagain.
I came back is because this is who
I am.
This is where I come from.
This is my family's heritage.
Right?
And I grew up with the knowledge and
the experience and the love of the land,
the hunting, the, you know, listening to the
elders' stories.
And I was one of the fortunate ones
when I came back and got the job
of land resource officer, had the opportunity to
listen to all the elders and their stories.
And so we've got a lot, a lot
of history here.
And so I take pride in my heritage.
And then this is why this is so
important to me.
This is why this whole area is so
important, because I can drive down the road
and I can show you where our people
were and I can show you where all
the moose I shot.
Keep it between us because that's important.
One of the things that that I'm able
to do is pass down my knowledge.
I'm getting to a point where I'm starting
to accept, not told, to be a teacher.
So now some of my nephews and nieces
are great hunters and I take pride in
that because I don't have to pack anymore.
I just talk them through it and have
a cup of tea and they can just
shoot it and I'll guide them to it.
And so, there's an excitement.
There's a connection with your family,
extended family when they're young and you teach
them something and you take pride when they're
able to say, uncle, uncle, I got a
moose.
Come, come watch me.
Right?
It's a beautiful thing because I can just
sit back and watch.
So, it goes on and on
and on.
Right?
And that's why it's so, so wonderful for
me to be able to share and hand
down my knowledge to the younger generation.